Both poles of our
planet are covered with ice
They're the largest and most demanding wildernesses of all
Nowhere else on
Earth is seasonal change so extreme
It causes the ice
to advance and retreat every year
And all life here
is governed by that
When the first
polar explorers headed south
Giant cathedrals
of ice marked their entry
Into uncharted territory
Passing the
towering spires
They must have
wondered what unearthly sights lay in store
As they battled on
The ice became
increasingly dominant
But nothing could
have prepared them
For the ice world
that finally loomed into view
Terra incognita
the unknown land
At the southernmost extreme of our planet
the continent of Antarctica is as large as the United States of America
90% of all the
world's ice is found here
This frozen world
is largely deserted
until the
start of spring
A daily penguins
In a hurry
The clock
is ticking
Instead of
waiting for the summer melt
The new arrivals
hasten south over the frozen sea
They have come
here to breed
But polar
summers are so short
They must be in
position before the thaw starts
As the sea
ice retreats
life can
journey farther south
Antarctic
waters are so rich
that visitors
come from far and wide
to harvest them
Vast numbers of
chinstrap penguins come ashore
to breed
No bird will lay
their eggs directly onto ice
So bare rock is
a vital commodity
The best patches
are worth the climb
The cliff tops
are soon stained pink
With the droppings of tens of thousands of nesting penguins
Only in a land
almost entirely covered in ice
could bare rock
be reckoned an oasis
Some will travel
into the heart of the continent to find it
These are nunatak
the exposed peaks
of vast mountain ranges
buried in ice
over a mile deep
The eerie
silence here
is only
broken in spring
The snow
petrels have arrived
and are courting
Antarctic petrels
now join the most southerly bird colony on Earth
The birds have flown inland for over 300 miles to reach this breeding site
Once their
eggs have hatched
they will be forced repeatedly to make the 600 mile round trip
to gather
food in the ocean
First though
valuable nesting
places must be defended from property thieves
After
laying their eggs
the petrels take
time out to clean their plumage
The South Polar
Skua is a formidable opportunist
But the skuas
have not chanced upon the petrels
They've been
waiting for them
These birds do
not need to go to the ocean for their food
The skewers can
survive further south than any other predator
By exploiting the
petrels' desperate need for bare rock
Even at the
height of summer
less than three
percent of Antarctica is free of ice
And nearly all of
that exposed rock is found in one place
The Antarctic Peninsula
Its long arm extends further north than the rest of the continent
So spring
arrives here first
The thaw
unlocks sheltered bays
That provide
refuge from the relentless battering
Of the
Southern Ocean
In the depths
something stirs
Humpback whales
They have travelled over 5000 miles to reach these waters
The whales are
harvesting krill
Shrimplike creatures that begin to swarm here
As soon as
the ice retreats
Diving into the
heart of the swarm
Teams of whales
spiral round each other
In close
coordination
Now they turn
blasting air
from their blowholes
and ascend
towards their prey
The krill
becomes concentrated
as the spiralling
net of bubbles draws inwards
The team of
whales work round the clock
for the boom
is shortlived
Summer is
already fading
and the whales
will soon be forced north
as winter returns
The sun's
influence diminishes
and the ocean
starts to freeze
The greatest seasonal change on our planet is underway
The ice grows at
an extraordinary rate
advancing two and
a half miles a day
In a matter of weeks
the continent
effectively doubles in size
Life flees
from Antarctica
But one creature
is just arriving
Every winter
emperor penguins
leave the comfort of their ocean home
and begin a
remarkable journey
They head towards
their breeding grounds
almost a
hundred miles inland
Eventually
the emperor penguins reach the place where they were hatched
An area sheltered
by icebergs trapped in the frozen ocean
Here
they will raise
the next generation
But first
each must
find a mate
Males begin
to serenade
And if a
female replies
they pair up
posing
like statues
New couples
quickly form a strong bond
They seem oblivious to the noisy crowd around them
To cement
their relationship
the male steps
out with his female
The brief
courtship complete
There isn't a
moment to lose
With so much
pressure to perform
Any male would
struggle to stay on top
Several
weeks later
and it seems that
most couplings were successful
But producing the
egg has taken its toll
The females no
longer have the energy to incubate
The male
takes over
It's still minus
20 degrees centigrade
So the transfer
must be done quickly
or else the
egg will freeze
With no bare
rock to nest on
The male tucks
the egg into a special pouch
Where he can
keep it warm
It requires an
extraordinary piece of teamwork
Driven by hunger
the exhausted females now return to the ocean on their own
repeating the epic journey they made with the males only a month before
Now the sun
barely appears above the horizon
As the
days shorten
its warmth is
withdrawn from the continent
With the
females gone
the colony undergoes a strange transformation
The males
shuffle into groups
their eggs still
tucked away above their feet
They lock together in tightly packed huddles
as they
struggle to keep warm
Speeding up the action reveals how these huddles constantly shift and change
As each penguin
works its way towards the warmer interior
Crammed
into this scrum
the birds are
remarkably good natured
But they
have to be
If the
huddle breaks
even for a moment
precious
heat escapes
It's imperative
they reform as quickly as possible
For only by
acting as one
Can the males
withstand the elements
And protect
their eggs
But their
greatest test lies ahead
As winter advances
frequent blizzards drive the temperature down
It's now 60
degrees below zero
The birds at the
edge of the huddle
Bear the brunt of
the hundred mile an hour winds
And so provide shelter to those taking their turn in the middle
Abandoned
by the sun
The males are
left alone with their eggs
To face
the coldest
darkest
winter on Earth
At the northern
extreme of our planet
the sun rises for
the first time in months
illuminating a
very different ice world
Unlike Antarctica
the Arctic is a
vast frozen sea
surrounded by land
Here
winter is
coming to an end
But this bleak
wilderness remains locked in ice
Eider ducks
break the silence
They have stayed
here braving the northern winter
Instead of flying
south to warmer climes
Flocks
40，000 strong
sweep across
the frozen wastes
They all have
the same goal
A polynya
a permanent
hole in the sea ice
Kept open throughout the winter by strong ocean currents
This unusual duck
pond provides an overnight sanctuary
And when
day breaks
a rare
chance to feed
Just ten metres
beneath the ice
the sea floor is
carpeted with dense mussel beds
These can only be
reached during a brief lull in the currents
The ducks must
quickly prize the mussels free
before the tide
starts to turn
The window of
opportunity is short
As the current
begins to build
it's up，up
and away
These permanent
holes in the ice
provide seafood
throughout the winter
The diners
attract others
In the Arctic
any breach in
the icy barrier
can be a lifeline
Muskrats can
create their own
These giants have
the strength to smash through the frozen crust
to graze on the
vegetation below
These icebreakers
create an opening for other overwinterers
Flocks of
ptarmigan
make unusual
grazing companions to the muskoxen
Whose entourage
grows throughout the day
This odd
assembly of vegetarians
doesn't
go unnoticed
An Arctic fox
The muskoxen have
recently given birth
For the fox
it's a
chance to scavenge
But half a ton
of mad hairy cow
is not to be
trifled with
The calves are
born well before the spring melt
Giving them a
head start when summer finally arrives
It must get to
grips with its new ice world
Benign one minute
lifethreatening the next
Even in spring
winds chill
to the bone
The calf must
stay close to its mother
To avoid getting
lost in the sudden blizzard
Arctic wolves
In the whiteout
the threat is
almost impossible to detect
But the muskoxen
instinctively retreat to higher ground
Forming a defensive ring around their calves
The adults present a barricade that few hunters could breach
But the wolves
need not risk injury today
A calf has been
left behind in the panic
With each
passing day
the sun climbs
higher in the sky
and its rays
strike the Arctic more directly
It's spring
and new life stirs
The polar bear cubs emerge from the den in which they were born
Their mother stretches her legs after five months under the snow
They're just
two months old
and instinctively follow her lead
A steep slope
makes the best site for a den
But it's a tricky
place to take your first steps
It may
look like fun
But this is
serious training for the task ahead
There's no
food on the slopes
And the family
will need to head out across the frozen sea
Before their
mother's milk runs dry
Two weeks later
they're ready
Out on the sea ice
the female can
hunt for seals
But it will take
all her mothering skills
to keep
her cubs safe
in this
dangerous world of ice
The annual
melt has begun
This is a challenging time for the bear family
One out of every
two cubs do not survive their first year
out on the ice
As the sun's
influence increases
the sea ice seems
to take on a life of its own
Glacial meltwaters pour from the land
mingling with the
sea and speeding up the thaw
The seascape is
in constant flux
as broken ice is
moved on by winds and currents
The ice is
becoming too weak
to support a
male polar bear
He attempts to
spread his weight
But the ice that
has supported him all winter
Is rapidly
disintegrating
Each year
as the
climate warms
The Arctic
holds less ice
This is a
disaster for polar bears
Without its
solid platform
They can't hunt
the seals they need
In order
to survive
This may be a
glimpse of the unstable future
faced by this
magnificent creature
As the ice
disappears
sea birds return
to the high Arctic
Little auks
arrive in their millions
In some ways
these birds are
the penguins of the north
They seek bare
rock on which to lay their eggs
And they look
rather like penguins too
Unlike Antarctica
the Arctic can
be reached by landbased predators
which is why little orcs have kept the ability to fly
They use screeslopes to protect their eggs
burrowing up to a
metre beneath the rocks
At the
height of summer
the sun never sets
but just
skims the horizon
before
rising again
Migrants
return to the Arctic
from far and wide
They've come to
make the most of the brief flush of food
and to
produce their young
Sandhill cranes
have travelled all the way from New Mexico
Their chicks join
the growing band of youngsters
Exploring
the tundra
For a few
months each year
the Arctic becomes the land of the midnight sun
and 24 hours
of daylight
allow animals to
feed around the clock
The Arctic fox
finally has enough food
to raise her
large family
If you choose to
nest in the open
You must be
prepared for a fight
Arctic skewers
will see off any trespassers
even large
vegetarians
The male polar bear's ice world has finally vanished beneath him
While the female
is still kept on land by her dependent cubs
The male can take
to the sea in search of food
Ducking and diving
He hopes to
ambush seals
Resting on the
remaining fragments of ice
In these new
surroundings
he is a surprisingly adept swimmer
Once an
extremely rare sight
polar bears have
recently been seen over 60 miles from the shore
There is now no
turning back for this bear
He's forced to
head out into deeper water
His giant front
paws help him to fight the ocean currents
He seems at
home in the sea
But he cannot
swim indefinitely
He will drown
if he doesn't
find land somewhere
In this vast ocean
Walruses are now
gathering on low lying islands
They gave
birth on sea ice
But with this
platform now gone
They need a new
place to haul out and nurse their young
After several days at sea
the male bear
finally makes landfall
drawn by pungent
smells emanating from the island
By the end
of summer
the bear has
lost half his weight
With the
ice long gone
he is forced onto
land in search of food
There will be no
easy meals on this island
Walruses are the
largest seals in the world
They weigh
over a ton
and are armed
with tusks a metre long
Exhausted
from his swim
the bear must
regain his strength
The next day
a sea fog
shrouds the island
The walruses
sense that they are in danger
Using the
fog as cover
the bear
approaches the herd
The adults close
ranks around their young
presenting a wall
of blubber and hide
He tests
the barrier
but it stands firm
It appears that
the world's largest land carnivore
has met his match
There must be a
chink in the armour somewhere
Not here
This female
walrus is shielding her pup
If he can just
prise her off
The bear's claws
and teeth can't penetrate her thick hide
With the herd
retreating to water
the bear must
move quickly
Having
failed with one
he heads
straight for another
The chance of his
first meal in months is slipping away
He seems
increasingly desperate
It's now or never
He must avoid the
stabbing tusks if he's to win
The flailing
walrus is immensely powerful
And drags the
bear away from the shallows
Towards the
safety of the herd
It slips
from his grasp
Only at the
height of summer
when bears are on
the verge of starvation
Will they risk
attacking such dangerous prey
It was a gamble
that this bear took
and lost
The stab wounds
he received from the walrus
are so severe
that he can
barely walk
The walruses
are calm again
Seemingly aware
that the injured bear
no longer poses a
threat to them or their young
Unable to feed
this bear
will not survive
If the global
climate continues to warm
and the Arctic
ice melts sooner each year
it's certain that
more bears will share this fate
At the southern
end of our planet
Fiery ribbons are
illuminating the winter skies
The aurora
australis
This light
brings no warmth
To the
male penguins
Who are
still huddling
Defying the
coldest conditions on the planet
Their ordeal is
drawing to a close
30 days
after it last set
the sun rises
once more on Antarctica
Their appalling
trials have all been for this
Each father has
just one meal left inside him
He's been
saving it all winter
This single feed
will sustain the chicks for a few more days
But the males
have not eaten for nearly four months
If they do
not eat soon
they and their
chicks will die
But there is hope
on the horizon
The females
are returning
and their bellies
are full with fish
As they approach
waves of excitement ripple through the huddle
Each female
calls to her mate
And he
recognising her song
trumpets back
Reunited，at last
The mother sees
her chick for the first time
She's keen to
start parenting
But the father
needs persuading
To surrender the
chick he's been caring for all winter
He must now put
his chick at risk
In these temperatures it could freeze in seconds
The male will
have to let go
Eventually
the transfer to
the mother is safely made
The chicks grow
quickly on a diet of fish and squid
Soon
they're
keen to explore
but always
with mother in tow
This chick is
less fortunate
Its mother has
not returned to claim it
Another orphan is
searching for a new family
But this female
already has a chick of her own
Some orphans receive too much mothering from penguins
whose own chicks
have not survived
The urge to
parent is so strong
that they will
compete with one another
to adopt any
chick they find
Many of these
squabbles end in tragedy
as the poor chick
is trampled to death
Those chicks that
do have parents quickly learn survival skills
Even in spring
they must huddle
together for warmth
just as their
fathers did in the depths of winter
A group of chicks
has got lost in the blizzard
Cold and
disorientated
they search
for the colony
It will
not be long
before the storm
claims its first victims
By early summer
the chicks are
surprisingly well developed
And now look
ready to take on the world
Those that
survive their first year
have the best
possible start in life
Thanks to the extraordinary hardships endured by their parents
Parents who
battled with the Antarctic winter
and won
In the Arctic
the two
polar bear cubs
are now independent of their mother
and they
briefly reunite
where their
home ranges overlap
Their time
together will be fleeting
Most of their
lives are now spent alone
Wandering the
vast tracts of frozen ocean
Following
their mother
has prepared
them for life at the pole
An ever
changing land
ruled by ice
Whether they are
ready for the bigger changes
that have begun
to shape the ice worlds of our planet
remains to be seen